Sara Nawaz

sara.a.nawaz@gmail.com

Squamish, BC Canada

Interdisciplinary social scientist researching the social and governance dimensions of novel climate and environmental technologies, via a mix of quantitative and qualitative methods. ~10 years of experience researching and working on issues of climate change, environment and social impact, including in the Global South.

Education:

Doctor of Philosophy (PhD), Resources, Environment, and Sustainability *University of British Columbia (UBC)*, Vancouver, British Columbia (BC), Canada

Master of Philosophy (MPhil), Development Studies *University of Oxford*, Oxford, United Kingdom (UK)

2011-2013

2017-2021

Desiration of Anto (DA) Major Francisco Miner Dul

Bachelor of Arts (BA), Major: Economics. Minor: Public Policy Swarthmore College, Swarthmore, Pennsylvania, United States (US)

2007-2011

Professional Experience

Postdoctoral Fellow, Institute for Science, Innovation and Society, University of Oxford
Oxford, UK
October 2021—present

Researching social and governance dimensions of marine carbon dioxide removal (CDR) as part of the EUfunded project "OceanNETs". OceanNETs is exploring the feasibility, risks and co-benefits of a range of marine NETs, with particular focus on ocean alkalinity enhancement.

Postdoctoral Fellow, Institute for Resources, Environment and Sustainability (IRES), UBC Vancouver, BC, Canada Sept 2021—present

Researching public and expert perceptions of marine CDR, as part of the Pacific Institute for Climate Solutions' project, "Solid Carbon", which is exploring the potential for an offshore NET that aims to turn carbon dioxide into rock.

Research Assistant (various appointments), IRES, UBC

Sept. 2017—Aug. 2021

Vancouver. BC. Canada

Contributed to the design, implementation, data collection, analysis, and writing for various studies on novel and emerging applications in agriculture and conservation. Contributions included design, implementation and statistical analysis of surveys, event ethnography fieldwork and analysis, and design, facilitation and analysis of interviews and focus group, amongst others.

Independent Consultant

Sept. 2016—Sept. 2017

Washington, DC, US

Hired by the World Wildlife Fund to conduct an ecosystem service valuation for several of Belize's marine protected areas.

Consultant, Environmental Resources Management

Sept. 2014—June 2016

Washington, DC, US

Managed and contributed to a variety of economic and social research projects for clients such as the World Bank, International Finance Corporation, and Inter-American Development Bank. Projects included economic, social and ecosystem service impact assessments, a global survey on sustainability in international finance, natural resource damage assessments, and ecosystem service valuations, amongst others. Received multiple awards for contributions to and leadership in project activities. In addition to research and analysis, projects often involved conducting fieldwork in Latin America, collaborating with teams across multiple continents, and presenting research findings to clients.

Research Assistant, World Resources Institute (WRI)

Washington, DC, US

Conducted research on behalf of WRI's President's speaking and writing. Contributed to other WRI projects such as WRI's four-year strategic plan, strategy for WRI's Forest and Landscape Restoration team, and a sustainability review of WRI's endowment.

Research Assistant, Oxford Martin Commission

May—Aug. 2013

Oxford, UK

Contributed to the Commission's flagship report titled "Now for the Long Term," on sustainably intensifying food production, boosting youth employment, and improving governance indicators.

Academic service

I have served as a reviewer for the Journal of Environmental Management, Agriculture and Human Values, and Elementa: Science of the Anthropocene.

Committee member, IRES Director Search Committee, UBC

March—May 2022

Represented postdoctoral fellows and research associates in search for and selection of a new IRES departmental director.

Co-president, IRES Student Society, UBC

July 2018-June 2019

Co-led department's student society. Activities involved events such as organizing welcome for new students, department's annual celebration, and a research slam. Also organized and led monthly student society meetings and served as a liaison between student body and faculty.

Co-Leader, Oxford Global Food Security Forum, University of Oxford

June 2012—June 2013

Organized, advertised, and facilitated a semester-long seminar series and organized an international conference on food security. The seminars and conference brought together 100+ social and natural scientists to engage in a multi- and interdisciplinary conversation on food security.

Organizer, Women in Development Forum, University of Oxford

Feb. 2013

Organized a pilot forum that brought together academics and professionals to speak to 60+ students about considerations around international development as a career path for women.

Writing Associate, The Writing Center, Swarthmore College

Sept. 2008—May 2011

Supported 12+ students each term in drafting and editing essays; also worked with individual students on a walk-in basis in the College's Writing Center.

Grants, Fellowships, and Awards

Nominee, IRES, CGS/ProQuest Distinguished Dissertation Award (2022)

UBC Four-Year Fellowship (2017-21)

UBC International Tuition Award (2017-21)

ERM Service Excellence Award (2015)

ERM Star Award (2015)

Oxford Department of International Development Fieldwork Award (2012)

Swarthmore Lucretia Mott Graduate Fellowship (2011—2013)

Swarthmore Foundation Grant (2011)

Swarthmore College Writing Associate Fellowship (2008—2011)

Swarthmore College Quadir Summer Research Fellowship (2009)

Sept. 2013—Sept. 2014

Peer-reviewed publications

Nawaz, S., & T. Satterfield. (*Accepted*) On the nature of naturalness? Theorizing 'nature' for the study of public perceptions of novel genomic technologies in agriculture and conservation. *Environmental Science and Policy*.

Nawaz, S., Satterfield, T. & Phurisamban, R. (*Accepted*) Does 'precision' matter? A Q study of public interpretations of gene editing in agriculture. *Science, Technology and Human Values.*

Nawaz, S., & Satterfield, T. (2022). Climate solution or corporate co-optation? US and Canadian publics' views on agricultural gene editing. *PLoS ONE*, *17*(3 March), e0265635. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0265635

Hagerman, S., Satterfield, T., **Nawaz, S.,** St-Laurent, G. P., Kozak, R., & Gregory, R. (2021). Social comfort zones for transformative conservation decisions in a changing climate. *Conservation Biology*, 35(6), 1932–1943. https://doi.org/10.1111/cobi.13759

Gregory, R., Kozak, R., Peterson St-Laurent, G., **Nawaz, S.**, Satterfield, T., & Hagerman, S. (2021). Under pressure: conservation choices and the threat of species extinction. *Climatic Change*, *166*(1–2), 1–21. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-021-03102-3

Nawaz, S., Satterfield, T., & Hagerman, S. (2021). From seed to sequence: Dematerialization and the battle to (re)define genetic resources. *Global Environmental Change*, *68*, 102260. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2021.102260

Nawaz, S., & Kandlikar, M. (2021). Drawing Lines in the Sand? Paths Forward for Triggering Regulation of Gene-Edited Crops. *Science and Public Policy*, 48(2), 246–256. https://doi.org/10.1093/scipol/scab014

Nawaz, S., Klassen, S., & Lyon, A. (2020). Tensions at the boundary: Rearticulating 'organic' plant breeding in the age of gene editing. *Elementa: Science of the Anthropocene*, 8(1), 34. https://doi.org/10.1525/elementa.429

Nawaz, S. Agroforestry in the Shadow of a Green Monster: The Politics of Confronting Hunger in the Northern Cauca, Colombia. 2013. Columbia University Journal of Global Health. https://doi.org/10.7916/thejgh.v3i1.5261

Conference presentations and guest lectures

"Engineering carbon removal: New technologies and social considerations." Resources, Environment and Sustainability (RES) 520 seminar: Climate Change: Science, Technology and Sustainable Development. Online. March 2022.

"Rearticulating 'organic plant breeding' in the age of gene editing?" Co-presented with Susanna Klassen. Organic Seed Grower's Conference. Online. February 2022.

"Social comfort zones in a transforming climate." American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting. Online. April 2021.

"Beyond naturalness? Social dimensions of gene editing in agriculture." Institute for Resources, Environment and Sustainability Student Symposium. Online. April 2021.

"Beyond 'precision': A Q-method study on public perceptions of gene editing and gene drives for agriculture." Conference on Gene Editing in Agriculture and Food. Online. October 2020.

"Owning seeds, owning sequences?" RES 507 seminar: Human Technological Systems. Vancouver, BC. February 2020.

"From seed to sequence: Making sense of debates over the dematerialization of agricultural genetic resources." Canadian Anthropology Association/American Anthropology Association Annual Meeting. Vancouver, BC. November 2019.

Languages | Spanish (Professional proficiency). **Software** | R, Qualtrics, NVivo.